Hello and Welcome to the complete crash course
on ruby programming I am Raghav and you can
find all my work on my website AutomationStepByStep.com
in this video we are going to learn everything
from scratch and we will start with a hello
world program in Ruby I will show you how
you can copy my project and then we will look
at comments variables we will look at how
to get user input from console strings operators
arrays and hashes in Ruby and then we will
move to conditional statements ternary statement
case statement for loop while and do while
loops we will look at until and unless keywords
break and next redo and retry keywords we
will see how to create methods and classes
and objects in Ruby so lets get started and
here I will go to repl.it this is a online
editor I am going to use you can go here and
create a free account I have created my free
account and here you can see I already have
some Repls I already have this here but I
am going to create a new Ripl or a new folder
I will click here you can also go from here
I will click here and select the language
so today we are going to learn Ruby I will
select Ruby and I will name this as Ruby crash
course and say create repl so this will create
a repl and we can start creating our Ruby
programs here so it is loading and here once
this is loaded you can go to the settings
and can select the layout side by side or
stacked I will say side by side then the theme
light or dark I will go with the dark theme
you can select the font size for my case it
is large indentation and all the settings
you can do from here and then here you can
write your code and can also create new files
see the files are here then here you can go
to version controlling packages database settings
we just want to go to the files here here
I can write my code and here I can see the
output it is also a shell I will show you
this later so now I can start typing here
so let's start with our hello world program
so in Ruby I can say puts Puts is to print
anything on the console and if I say hello
world and if I run this you can see the output
here it says hello world now I can also say
p and say something here So p is the short
form for puts it will be the same thing you
can see it prints this here now I can also
save print hello again and if I run it now
you can see it is printing hello again as
well however after printing it did not move
the cursor to the next line so this is the
difference between puts and print puts Moves
the cursor to the next line after printing
and print does not move it if you want you
can also create a new file here if you want
to have easy categorisation you can do like
this and now if I say something here puts
hello if I now run this you will see it is
still running our main.rb and if you want
to run this file will have to load it here
I will say load and I will say hello dot RB
and now if you go here and run it will now
Run your files so it is saying hello there
so you can do that but for now let me just
keep on this file so this is a hello world
program now you can also get all my Ruby project
so if you want this Ruby project you can just
go to this link repl.it Ruby crash course
so this is my link and if you go to your browser
and just hate this link you will get my entire
project Ruby project from here and even if
we do not create account on repl.it you can
still copy my entire project from here and
if you want you can do a forking so here you
can see all my project is here and you can
get it from here so let me just leave this
and come back and now let us go to comments
so how do you create comments now if I go
here and if I have to comment everything,
i will select everything and press CTRL and
Forward slash / on my keyboard if you are
on mac press CMD and forward slash / and it
will comment out everything and it will put
a hash # here so for a single line comments
you put hash for a single line comment and
if you want a multiline comment so if I want
to put everything inside comments I can say
=begin and then =end so everything inside
this block will be a comment so this is how
you can do commenting let us come to variables
so we can give any variable name let us Say
I Say name equals and I can give value so
this is a variable and then I can say puts
or print name and if I run this you will see
it is printing this here and then I can have
a numerical variable or a numerical value
in a variable I can say 123 or I can have
a Boolean value I can say condition = true
and then I can print everything I can say
puts and I can also say like this name coma
num coma condition and if I now run this it
will print everything here so this is how
you can use all these variables and store
values inside your variables now here if you
want to print something I can say hello and
if you want to refer this variable name you
will have to say hash and in { give the variable
name and if I now run this it will say hello
Raghav so you can do interpolation or refer
variables like this in Ruby how to get input
from user console so let us say let me comment
everything I will press control and / on my
keyboard and now lets say I want to get something
from the user in that case I will say a gets
dot chomp this is the function we use and
before this I will save print enter your name
and then I will say gets dot chomp and this
will get the user input from the console and
let me put this in a variable called name
and then I can print hello and then I can
say hash name if I now run this on the console
it is saying enter your name I will say Raghav
and hit enter It is saying hello Raghav now
just in case you want to get a integer or
want to convert this into an integer if I
say print enter your ID in that case I will
create a variable and again say gets dot chomp
but in this case I will convert it to integer
so i will say dot to underscore i this is
convert to integer and then I can print hello
name and say your ID is hash ID and if I now
run this it says enter your name I say my
name is Raghav and then it says enter your
ID I say 10 it says hello Raghav your ID is
10 so this is how you can get a user input
from console let us learn about Strings so
here I will comment this control / and now
I can say I can give any variable name str1
and say this is a string I can also use a
' instead of " this will also work fine this
is another string and I can say puts str1
and puts str2 and if I now run this it will
run and say there is some issue let me check
ok so this is str2 I forgot here let me run
it now again and now this is saying this is
a string and this is another thing so this
is working fine now we have a lot of string
operations in Ruby how to create multi line
string so if I have to create a multiline
string I can say STR 3 = this inside "and
saying this is a and I will present enter
multiline again press enter string Now You
See I have just pressed enter and if I now
say puts str3 and run this let us see the
output so it is printing it as it is so I
just have to put the string in a different
Line or what I can do is I can say STR 3 = percentage
and / and / and inside this forward slashes
I can write my string I can say this is my
string and if I want to print it I will say
puts STR let me say STR4 here we have already
used str3 here now if I run this you can see
it is also printing my multiline string like
this I can do multiline string interpolation
is how do you refer variables in string and
this we have already seen here so you just
say hash and the variable name inside { to
do interpolation or referring of variables
let us see how can I get length and can do
upcase downcase I have a string say STR5 and
I say it is hello now I can say puts STR5
dot size OR I can say puts STR5 dot length
if I run this let us see the output so it
is printing the size or length of my string
I will comment this earlier part and now if
I have to do upcase or downcase I can say
puts STR5 dot upcase OR STR5 dot downcase
if I run this is it will convert it to uppercase
or lowercase and you can see it has converted
it like this and then I can also say puts
STR5 dot reverse if I want to reverse my string
I can use the dot reverse function and you
can see it has reversed I can also reverse
after doing upcase so downcase I am saying
upcase and then reverse so I will say reverse
and if I now run this it is converting it
to an uppercase and then reversing my string
then I can say include so I can say STR5 dot
include and if I give something let us say
hello and if I run this it will say true that
means this is a part of the string if I use
something else like with capital at H Hello
and run this now it is saying false that means
this is not part of this string and then I
can concatenate my strength so for example
I want I have multiple things I can say hello
and then I can just give space and again give
the next part how are you you and if I run
this you will see it will concatenate and
then print it on the console so let me very
quickly check this I will clear my console
and run it again and you can see it is saying
hello how are you the other ways I can also
put a plus in between and this will also work
if I run this now it is still printing the
same thing or I can say hello dot concat and
then I can give the next part I can say how
are you and I will run this and you will see
it is now printing it as it is so this is
how you can concatenate strings then you can
also freeze your strings let us say I will
say STR6 = hi and I will print this and then
I will modify this string I will say STR6
= STR6 and then I will append something hi
again and then I will print it again STR6
let us see the output I will just comment
all this control / or cmd / on my keyboard
and yes I'm here now I will run this and let
us see what happens so it has modified the
string Hi again and now if I say STR6 dot
freeze so I have freezed my string and if
I now try to modify it again let us see what
happens now if I run this it says there is
an exception you cannot modify a frozen string
so if you want that nobody should be able
to modify your setting you can use dot freeze
operation and then if you want to compare
two strings you can use double equals to for
example I have this string I can say = = ABC
and if I run this it will print true let me
comment out this one and then run again and
you will see here true if I say I can also
say abc dot equal and then I can say something
and if I run this now it will say false so
these are two ways how you can compare strings
so all this we have learnt you can also use
this length and you can get something out
of your string using all these operations
let me just copy this from here and paste
it here suppose we have a string called message
and then you can just say puts message hello
and if it is a part of the sting it will printed
so here it is printing it then you can use
these index positions to print some particular
part of your settings if I say message 0 it
is printing h if I say message 0 to 4 it is
printing HAL that is the first 4 characters
I can use a range here I am saying 0 to 20
inside square brackets and it is printing
the 0 to 20 characters I can say zero until
the length of the string so it is now printing
the entire setting I can go from reverse that
is from the back side of the string using
minus So if I say minus 4 it is printing the
fourth character from the back which is S
here this one and then I can also print the
length as we have seen earlier so this are
Sting operations Let us move to operators
and I will comment everything now let us move
to operators now in Ruby we have all these
mathematical operators and then we also have
these comparison operators so there are multiple
operators let me very quickly copy this code
to save some time and I will just copy it
here so you can do addition using + operator
- subtraction using minus - operator multiplication
using the star * and then this is divide / and
this is modular % so this will give you the
result as the remainder of this division so
when you use percentage it will show you remainder
of the division and this is exponential ** so
if you use this double star this is 2 raise
to the power 3 and then this is comparison
== if 2 is equals to 3 this will check not
equals this will check greater than less than
greater than equal to and less than equal
to Let me run everything and check and you
can see it is now printing all this so you
can get this code and try it out let us now
move to ternary operator so here let us say
I say A = 10 B = 20 and then if I say C = I
can say give a condition A is greater than
B and then I'll give a ? and then I say A
and coln B so what does this mean is in ternary
operator we give an expression or condition
here and then a question mark if this condition
is true this will be the output of this will
get stored in C if the condition is false
after colon : whatever the expression we have
will get executed so condition if true this
will get executed if false this will get executed
and then finally I will say puts greater number
is and I will say C so let us see I will run
this and check and it says given number is
20 so this is how you can use a ternary operator
Let us move to Arrays and before I do that
I will have to comment everything and now
Let us move to arrays now in Ruby you can
create an array I can say give any variable
name like array1 equals and I can give these
square brackets so this will create an empty
array or I can also se array2 = array dot
new both of these ways create array and in
this case it has created an empty array if
I try to check the length or size of these
arrays I will say array1 dot size and I can
say puts array2 dot size or length this will
be the same I run this and you can see it
is printing 0 0 so that means they are of
zero size or empty I can just give us size
here so if I say bracket 10 and now if I run
this you can see the second array is of size
10 and for the first array if I want I can
directly give the values here so now if I
run this you will see first array is of size
5 and the second array is of size 10 so this
is how you can create arrays now we have all
these functions I can get something access
element at a particular index using dot at
function so I can say puts aray 1 dot and
I can say at and then I can say in the square
brackets [] I can say what index I want let
you say 2 and if I run this you can see here
there is some issue let me very quickly check
and I have to use a circular bracket () and
not a square bracket [] I will run this sorry
for that and check again and it is saying
empty because there is nothing at this position
I will say 2 and if I run this you can see
it will print 3 that means at index position
2 we have 3 because the index position starts
from 0 so this is index position 0 this is
1 and this is 2 and then I can use fetch now
if you say this you can see the difference
here I will say puts array1 dot fetch and
I will again say give some position here are
you can see the difference when I say at 10
it gave me empty and did not give me any error
but when I say fetch at 10th index it will
give me an error that is is array index outside
the array bounds if you want to get this error
then you can use fetch let me very quickly
comment this out and then I can use first
and last I can say puts array1 dot first and
puts array1 dot last it will print the first
and last element of the array and you can
see one and five here then I can say take
n and IT returns the first n elements of the
array example if I say puts array1 dot take
and I say 2 here and run you will see it is
printing the first n elements that is the
first two elements from this array then I
can say push to add the items to the end let
me very quickly just use all this to save
some time and I will have to remove this and
I will say array1 dot push and I will say
6 array1 and I will say 7 array1 dot let us
say 0 array1 dot at this position insert 4
so what does all this mean when I say push
it will add item to the end of the array when
I use this symbol to append it will again
add to the end and if you want to add at the
beginning or the start you can say unshift
and when you want to add any object or element
at a particular location you can use insert
and give the index position and then the object
so now after all this when I say puts array1
you will see the difference so I say this
and now if I run let us see I will have to
stop and clear my console and run again and
check ok yes there was some error I can go
back to my earlier project and go to arrays
so this is what I have here just to make sure
I if I making any mistake I will check this
so let me try to print this and check puts
or print and the same thing I will print for
here and here and here so I will run it again
and check and yes this time looks like this
is running but it is all printing in the same
line so I will add a puts in between so it
changes to the next line and then I can check
the the errors and exceptions so let me do
this and clear the console and run it so here
this is all fine you can see it has added
6 here than It has added 7 then it added 0
which is what we did here unshift and zero
I will try to delete this puts I will clean
and say I do not want actually want this let
me just say puts and run and let us see and
yes this is all working fine so we have done
all these operations and then we can say drop
now drop will return elements after n elements
have been dropped so if I say a print array1
dot drop and I will say 2 and if I run it
now so you can see it has dropped the first
two elements and then it is it is not printing
our array then we can say Pop Pop will remove
it from the end the element from the end shift
will remove element from the start delete
a particular element will remove the specific
item for example if I say here I say array1
dot delete and i will say delete 3 and now
if I run this it has removed 3 and now if
you print your array there will be no 3 there
so let me say print array 1 and run this I
should be using print here and puts will just
move it to the next line I will run this again
and check and now you can see 3 is removed
from the array then we can use unique it will
remove any duplicate items in your array if
you see my array now if I run this and check
my array you can see 4 here is multiple times
so I will say array 1 dot unique and run it
now you can see 4 is removed and now we only
have all the unique values in our array so
this is all about Array Now let's go to hashes
now array store information or values within
the numerical index and we have seen that
we can use the numerical index to access our
arrays now Hashes store information using
key value pair and you can create a hash like
this so for example let me just comment all
this and now I can say hash 1 = I can give
a { and this is a empty hash and now if I
want I can add the key and value I can say
name and I can say equals and this Arrow and
then I can say give value and then I can also
say here I can give a coma and add more values
I can say subject and I can say here automation
and then I can again give a , and in the next
line I will say topic and then I can give
here the topic name so this is the hash I
can say puts hash one dot size and if I now
run this you can see it is saying 3 now the
other way of creating a hash is I can copy
this and I will say hash 2 you can give any
name and now here instead of this I can use
a colon and so this is also a valid way of
creating hashes and I can also print its size
I can say hash 2 size and if I run this this
is printing 3 again now if I have to access
anything in my Hashes I can just use the square
brackets and use the key for example I can
say puts hash one and here I will say name
and if I run this it is getting Raghav here
or I can say puts hash 2 and if I say topic
and if I now run this now here it is not printing
anything so I will choose a colon and I think
outside let me check like this and run this
and now I am getting Ruby here so this is
how you can use and access hashes and you
can also use a loop to get all the values
from your hashmap or hashes so let's say I
will say hash 1 dot each and I say do and
in this pipe symbol I say key value and then
I say puts inside the loop and then I say
hash key and hash value so it will get the
Key and value out of the hash let me copy
it again here and say hash 1 and now if I
run this and now it is running and printing
the keys and the values this was about hashes
Let us not go to if else conditions in Ruby
and in Ruby you can create IF ELSE conditions
and this is the syntax if the condition and
the code and then end so let us create a if
else condition I will comment this and now
I will say if 2 is greater than 1 then I want
to print 2 is Greater and then I will say
end if I now run this it is saying 2 is Greater
or if I say I will say age = 18 and in the
if condition I say If age is greater than
18 then print you are eligible to drive now
if I run this because this condition now will
not be true let us see the output I will clear
everything stop clear and then again you can
now see it is not printing anything because
this condition becomes false and it comes
out of the if statement so to have something
after it becomes false I can say else and
I can say puts you are not eligible to drive
and now if I run this here you will see it
is printing you are not eligible to drive
now you can also say have a multiple else
if so I can say elsif and then I can say else
if age is less than or equal to 18 then print
this and finally I say else print enter a
valid input so now if I say age is20 and run
it will say you are eligible to drive if it's
less than 18 it will say you are not eligible
to drive and then if you have any invalid
input it will go to the else block so this
is if else and if statements ternary we have
already seen it is a kind of a short form
of if else where we give expression and then
question mark if this expression is true this
is executed if it is false this is executed
we have already seen this Let us goto case
let us say I have a array called days and
I can have values like ok or I can have values
like 1 2 3 4 5 6 and 7 and then I say case
and I will say when one then I will have to
say case day so it switches to day and then
I say when one I will say puts today is is
Monday and then I say when two then say today
is Tuesday and so on and if it does not match
anything than I can say else puts enter valid
input so I can also get this from a user I
can say print entered a number and then I
will get it into a variable called day using
gets dot chomp dot to integer and let's see
what happens now I will say run and it says
ok the issue was this was my mistake I also
have to end this I did not end it now I will
run this and now it say enter number I say
one and today is Monday I run it again I say
two it says today is Tuesday and if I give
something else here then it says enter a valid
input so this is how you can use case statements
and here in other programming languages it
is kind of switch case where switch comes
instead of case and then instead of when we
have cases this is the syntax in Ruby let
us go and see for loop now I will comment
this in Ruby I can say for i in 1 to 10 this
is a range and then I will say puts i and
say end and if I run this it will print 1
to 10 I can also use a array I can say for
i in this array 12345 and I will say puts
i and say end and this is the same thing if
I run this it will print all these elements
of the array so this is how you can use for
loop then coming to while and do while loop
so while loop executes while condition is
true so I can say while condition and then
do and then end so I can say here let us say
while say X = 1 and I say while X is less
than 10 do I will say print X and I will also
make X increment by 1 I can say x = x + 1
or I can also se X + = 1 which is the same
thing and then I will end the while loop I
will clear and run and you can see it painting
1 to 9 this is because we set less than 10
if I say less than equal to 10 and then again
this will now print from 1 to 10 now in a
do while loop it is similar to while loop
the only difference is that it will execute
at least once so let us see this code this
is how we use a do while loop and i will comment
this so we say loop do and this is our code
I am saying enter a number greater than 10
and I am getting a input from user and if
I say If number is greater than 10 then I'm
saying break that is coming out of the loop
so if I run this it says Enter a number greater
than 10 if I say 6 which is less than 10 it
is still going in the loop until I give a
number which is greater than 10 it will not
come out now I say 20 and now it will come
out of the loop so this is how you can use
a do while loop in Ruby now going to until
and unless conditions so until will execute
until the given condition evaluates to true
and let me show you this code here here I
say i = 1 and I say until i = = 10 it will
keep on printing i and I am also incrementing
I with one and here if I run this you will
see until the condition is true it will keep
on running the loop and then unless executes
the code until or unless the condition is
false if the condition is true code specified
in the else clause is executed so let me show
you unless as well here I am saying x = 3
and saying unless x is less than 5 x is greater
or equal to 5 else put this so if this condition
is false only then it will execute this if
I run this you can see it says x is less than
5 which is printing this because this condition
is true so you can use unless like this then
we have break and next we use break and next
in loops break is used to come out of the
loop and next is used to skip that particular
iteration of the loop let me show you an example
if I say x = 1 and I say while x is less than
or equals 10 and here I am adding a condition
if x becomes equals to 5 then break out of
the loop and if I run this and check you will
see it is going until four and as soon as
X becomes 5 it is coming out of the loop however
if I want to skip a particular iteration of
a loop I can use next so if I use this I will
comment this and if I say I am using a for
loop I am saying for i in 1 to 10 and as i
becomes 5 I am saying next so it will skip
this I will run and check you can see it is
printing 1 2 3 4 and 5 is not getting printed
because this is keeping that iteration and
going to the rest of the loop this is how
and when you can use break and next Let us
see Redo and Retry Redo is to repeat the current
iteration of the loop let us see an example
I will say x equals one and while x is less
than 5 I am printing x and also incrementing
x to 1 and then I am saying Redo if x = = 5
that means when this condition becomes true
the current iteration of the loop will get
executed let us see if I don't to this what
happens I will not use this or comment this
out and run my code you can see here it is
printing 1 to 4 it is not printing 5 because
we are saying x less than 5 if I run with
the Redo I say redo if x = = 5 now you will
see here it is also printing 5 because as
this condition becomes true it is Re executive
that particular iteration of the loop and
then retry is to repeat the whole loop iteration
from start and retry statement only works
inside begin and rescue block let me show
you I will copy this and paste it here I am
saying for i in 1 to 10 and using a begin
I am raising an exception if i become 10 and
in the rescue section I am saying retry so
what is will do it when i becomes 10 it will
retry the iteration and it will keep on doing
this it will be kind of a infinite loop if
I try to run this you will see it will be
infinite and I will have to stop it manually
so you can see it is it will keep on running
until I stop it so this is redo and retry
let us now go to methods in Ruby so we use
methods or functions so that we have a modular
code and it is a block of code that returns
a value or you may also have a method without
returning any value and we use methods so
that we can run the same code again and again
and we have reusability and in Ruby we use
the keyword def so we say deaf and give a
method name and then I can put any code let
us say hello from method and then I say end
and if I run this now nothing happens because
we are actually not calling this method to
execute method we have to call this method
so I will say hello and now if I run you will
see it is saying hello from method it is a
good practice to give brackets here it can
be empty arguments but this is how we create
a method so it is printing hello from method
now I can also give some arguments of parameters
let us say user and then I will say I will
prefer this variable user here and now if
I run this you will see there is an exception
because now this method is accepting one argument
and we are not providing any argument while
we are calling the method so I have to provide
the argument or a value or a parameter here
I say Raghav and if i now run this it is saying
hello Raghav here I can have have multiple
parameters as well I can say user and ID and
here I will say your ID is and I will say
hash and ID I will provide two parameters
and I will say run and you will see here it
says hello Raghav your ID is 10 so this is
how you can create methods in Ruby and now
I can call this with multiple parameters so
this is now reusable I can say John and say
20 and if I now run this hello Raghav your
ID is10 and hello John your id is 20 so now
this is reusable code Let us see classes and
objects in Ruby if you have to create a class
in Ruby you just have to use a Keyword called
class and then you can give it any name let
us say i say car you have to say end to end
the class inside the class you can have any
variables and methods let us say I have a
method I say get name and then inside this
I will say puts car name is now here let us
say I have to call this method so I will have
to create an object of the class and to create
object of the class you can give any variable
like car1 this will be the instance of this
object or the instance of the class and we
are calling referring this instance or object
with this variable car1 and then I say car
dot new so this is now created an object of
the car and we are calling it car1 and with
this I can access the variables and methods
now I can access car1 dot get name and if
I now run this you will see there is a issue
now I should not be using the curly brackets
here that was a mistake and now if I use this
object object reference car1 I can access
the methods of this class I can say get name
and if I now run this it says car name is
star star star this is what we are printing
here now I can create some variables in the
class I can say @ name this is a instance
variable that we create using the @ symbol
and a class variable we can create by double
@@ symbol now I can say this @ name now if
I say hash and inside  I refer this and
if I run this now you can see it is saying
car name is empty because we have not yet
set this variable so I can use another function
I can say set name and inside this I will
get a argument called name or carname inside
this function at name equals to whatever I
am getting here and before I call this I will
call set name function and here I can give
the name let us say toyota and now if I run
this you can see it is saying card name is
Toyota so this is how you can set the variables
like this and now this variable can be used
anywhere now sometimes we want to force the
user to give some arguments whenever creating
object of a class in that case I can use a
function called initialise Now initialise
is kind of a constructor if you know about
Java or other languages where we force a user
to give some arguments whenever creating objects
so let us say I have name and I have top speed
and then in the initialize function I take
name model and top speed and then inside the
function I say all these variables I say this
equals to name this will get equal to whatever
model we provide here and this will store
the top speed that we provide here and now
if you see I can just remove this set name
and if i now try to run my program you will
see there is a exception because now it says
this initialise needs three arguments and
we have not given any argument so we need
to give the arguments as soon as we create
the object of the class that is here so here
I have to give the object I will say here
I will give have to give the arguments I will
say Mercedes and let us say 2020 and let us
say top speed hundred and now if I I run this
you will see it is now there is some error
let me very quickly check it says undefined
local variable yeah there is some issue this
should be top speed so there was a typo I
will now clear and then run again and now
you can see it says card name is Mercedes
and similarly you can access model top speed
now also if you want if you go to shell you
can just say Ruby and give the name of your
Ruby file and run this from here it will still
run your Ruby program from here as well so
you can also use shell from here and then
you can get all my course all my Ruby course
with this URL if you go to your browser and
just open this URL I will also have this in
the description of this video so you can get
from description and then if you need any
more help you can always go to my website
that is automation step by step dotcom and
you will find all these courses here under
the program section I hope this was very useful
for you and if you have any issues let me
know never stop learning and I will see you
soon thank you for watching